Howard Wise Gallery
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Exhibition Files, 1957-1968, Series 3:; (Boxes 6-7; 0.75 linear ft.)
  Exhibition files for shows presented at the Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture, Cleveland, and the Howard Wise Gallery, New York, contain correspondence, printed material and guest lists. The series, however, is incomplete with very few files documenting exhibitions of the Howard Wise Gallery in New York, including the the New York gallery's opening show.
  Files are arranged chronologically.
  - Six from Paris (Cleveland opening show, Dec. 7, 1957-Jan. 18, 1958; Corneille, Barre, Bertrand, Levee, Gillet), 1958-1959, undated (Box 6)
  - Space - Light - Color (Cleveland, Jan. 19-March 9, 1958; Dorazio, Mitchell, Istrati), 1958 (Box 6)
  - Nature Forms in Art (Cleveland, March 9-April 20, 1958; Edwards, Peck, Mosca); Graphic Works of Hartung and Other Artists of the New School of Paris (Cleveland, March 30-[April ?], 1958; Atlan, Bissiere, Bryen, Esteve, Friedlaender, Hayter, Poliakoff, Singer, Springer), 1958 (Box 6)
  - Willi Baumeister and Five Contemporary German Painters (Cleveland, April 20-May 1958; Cavael, Jaenisch, Nay, Trier, Winter), 1958 (Box 6)
  - Bizyuta BunkBa Kyokai Art Association, Japan (Cleveland, May 28-June 29, 1958), 1957-1958, undated (Box 6)
  - Six Young Painters of the Howard Wise Gallery (Cleveland, June 30-July 1958; Bertschmann, Kane, Kessanlis, Quinn, Reeves, Soviak), 1958 (Box 6)
  - An Exhibition of Paintings by Xavier Gonzalez (Cleveland, Sept. 21-Oct. 19, 1958), 1958 (Box 6)
  - An Exhibition of Oils by 8 Painters of the Galerie Arnaud, Paris (Cleveland, Oct. 19-Nov. 18, 1958; Garrode, Dowling, Feito, Fichet, Gautier, Guitet, Koenig, Tanaka), 1957-1961, undated (Box 6)
  - Survey of Contemporary English Painting (Cleveland, Nov. 23-Dec. 27, 1958; Blow, Gear, Feiler, Frost, Hitchens, Vaughan, Wilson, Wynter), 1958 (Box 6)
  - 18 Painters of the 1958 Pittsburgh International (Cleveland, Dec. 28, 1958-Jan. 30, 1959), 1958 (Box 6)
  - Recent Paintings by Milton Resnick (Cleveland, Jan. 10-Feb. 10, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Fred Mitchell (Cleveland, Feb. 1-28, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Selections from the 1958-59 Whitney Annual (Cleveland, March 1-22, 1959), 1958-1959 (Box 6)
  - Adja Yunkers (Cleveland March 22-April 19, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Loan Exhibition, Art To-Day Around the World (Cleveland at Intown Club, April 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Recent Accessions (Cleveland, April 19-May 17, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Gabor Peterdi (Cleveland, May 20-June 26, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Group Show (Cleveland, Sept. 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Georgy Kepes (Cleveland, Sept. 20-Oct. 17, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Group Show (Cleveland, Oct. 4-29, 1959; Briggs, Dugmore, Grillo, Krasner, McNeil, Mitchell, Pace, Resnick), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Teenage Paintings from Israel (Cleveland, Oct. 18-25, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Ethel Edwards (Cleveland, Oct. 25-Nov. 21, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - James Johnson (Cleveland, Nov. 22-Dec. 19, 1959), 1959 (Box 6)
  - 6 of Paris (Cleveland, Dec, 20, 1959-Jan. 9, 1960; Sugaï, Levee, Barré, Gillet, Corneille), 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - Recent Paintings by Milton Resnick (Cleveland, Jan. 10-Feb. 29, 1960), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Four Contemporary English Painters (Cleveland, Feb. 14-March 12, 1960; Bell, Frost, Hilton, Turnbull), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Present Day Paris Painting (Cleveland, March 13-April 9, 1960; Bertrand, Francken, Corneille, Levee, Istrati, Koenig, Dumitresco), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Stephen Pace (New York, March 29-April 23; Cleveland, April 10-May 7, 1960), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Near-Cleveland Invitational Exhibition (Cleveland, May 8-June 4, 1960), 1958-1960, undated (Box 6)
  - Some Painters from Tenth Street (Cleveland, June 6-July 12, 1960), 1960 (Box 6)
  - The Works of Edward Dugmore (Cleveland, Sept 8-Oct. 1, 1960), 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - Loan Exhibition (Cleveland at Women's City Club, circa Oct. 1-circa Dec. 15, 1960), 1960-1961 (Box 6)
  - Elaine de Kooning (Cleveland, Oct. 31-26, 1960), 1960 (Box 6)
  - Augustus Peck (Cleveland, Nov. 29-Dec. 24, 1960), 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - Harry Bertschmann (Cleveland, Dec. 27, 1980-Jan. 21, 1961), 1957-1960 (Box 6)
  - Drawings by Auguste Rodin, Watercolors by George McNeil, and Prints by Stanley William Hayter (Cleveland, Jan. 23-Feb. 18, 1961), 1961, undated (Box 6)
  - A Selection of Paintings and Watercolors by Piero Dorazio (Cleveland, Feb. 20-March 18, 1961), 1961 (Box 6)
  - Movement in Art (Cleveland, March 20-April 15, 1961; Agam, Corneille, Lye, Tinguely), 1961 (Box 6)
  - Recent Paintings by James Johnson (Cleveland, April 17-May 13, 1961), 1961 (Box 6)
  - Works of Art Acquired by Cleveland Collectors Through the Howard Wise Gallery (Cleveland, May 15-June 10, 1961), 1961 (Box 6)
  - Recent Paintings by Fred Mitchell (Cleveland, June 12-July 8, 1961), 1961 (Box 6)
  - George McNeil and Stephen Pace (traveling exhibition), 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - General Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Refusals, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Transportation, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Rose Art Museum, Brandeis University (Nov. 6-Dec. 17, 1961), 1961 (Box 6)
    - Walker Art Center (Jan. 14-Feb. 18, 1962), 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Columbus Gallery of Fine Arts (March 1962), 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Arts Club of Chicago (June 11-30, 1962), 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    - Kalamazoo Art Center (July 10-Sept. 7, 1962), 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Move: On the Kinetic Sculpture (New York, Jan. 9-Feb.1, 1964), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Recent Paintings by Milton Resnick (New York, Feb. 4-29, 1964), 1964 (Box 6)
  - The Ten U.S.A. Sculptors of the 1963 Sao Paulo Bienal (New York, March 5-28, 1964), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Debut: First New York Showing of Three Young American Artists (New York, Sept. 29-Oct. 17, 1964; Celentano, Komodore, Raisen), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Vesey's Gala Garden (New York, May 27-June 19, 1964), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Paintings by George McNeil (New York, Oct. 20-Nov. 7, 1964), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Group Zero: Mack, Piene, Uecker (New York, Nov. 12-Dec. 5, 1964), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Stanley William Hayter - Peter Sedgley - Ulfert Wiulkie: Three One-Man Shows (New York, Jan. 12-20, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Oster's Magic Moirés (New York, Feb. 4-27, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Len Lye's Bounding Steel Sculptures (New York, March 6-April 3, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Computer-Generated Pictures by Bela Julesz and Michael Noll (New York, April 6-24, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Herbert Bayer - Charles Howard - Charmion Von Wiegand: Three One-Man Shows (New York, April 27-May 15, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - New Faces - New York (New York, May 18-June 18, 1965; Feitelson, Levi, Mattox, Nesbitt, Nizuma), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Lowell Nesbitt: Flowers, Facades and IBM Machines (New York, Sept. 21-Oct. 9, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Cinecromaticos by Abraham Palatnik of Brazil; Površine by Ivan Picelj of Yugoslavia: Two One-Man Shows (New York, Oct. 12-30, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Otto Piene, Light Ballet (New York, Nov. 2-20, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Bernard Schultze (New York, Nov. 23-Dec. 11, 1965), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Hans Haacke, Wind and Water; Gerald Oster, Moirés and Phosphenes (New York, Jan. 4-22, 1966), 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Julio Le Parc (New York, Feb. 1-19, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Yvaral (New York, Feb. 23-March 12, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Bill Komodore (New York, March 15-April 2, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Heinz Mack, Lights of Silver (New York, April 5-30, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Paintings by Francis Celentano; Sculptures in Stone by Minoru Nizuma (New York, May 3-28, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Bruno Munari (New York, Sept. 20-Oct. 8, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Peter Sedgley (New York, Oct. 11-29, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Gunther Uecker (New York, Nov. 1-19, 1966), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Lowell Nesbitt: Interior Spaces (New York, Nov. 22-Dec. 10, 1968), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Earl Reiback, A Festival of Light (New York, Dec. 13, 1966-Jan. 7, 1967), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Recent Works by George Ortman (New York, Jan. 10-28, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Lights in Orbit (New York, Feb. 4-March 4, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Julio Le Parc (New York, March 11-April 1, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Takis: Magnetic Sculpture (New York, April 7-29, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Charles Mattox: Kinetic Sculpture; and Fluorescent Painting by Herbert Aach (New York, May 9-June 3, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Marta Minuhin's Minuphone Booth (New York, June 27-July 28, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - The Paintings of George McNeil (New York, Sept. 19-Oct. 7, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Four Young Artists (New York, Oct. 14-Nov. 4, 1967; Hogle, McClanahan, Matisse, Van Saun), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Billy Apple's U.F.O.'s (Unidentified Fluorescent Objects) (New York, Nov. 11-Dec. 2, 1967), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Festival of Lights (New York, Dec. 9, 1967-Jan. 6, 1968), 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - George Ortman (New York, Jan. 13-Feb. 3, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Hans Haacke (New York, Jan. 13-Feb. 3, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Earl Reiback (New York, Feb. 10-March 11, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Howard Jones (New York, March 9-30, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Thomas Wilfred's Lumia Composition, "Cuccata Opus 162 in Three Movements" (New York, March 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Tony Martin's Game Room and "Invironment" (New York, April 6-May 4, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Tsai: Cybernetic Sculpture (New York, May 11-June 1, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Summer Lights (New York, [?]-July 26, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Niizuma: Stone and Canvas Sculptures (New York, Oct. 5-25, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Tom Lloyd: Kinetic Light Sculptures (New York, Nov. 2-23, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
  - Fun on 57th Street (New York, Nov. 30-Dec. 31, 1968), 1968 (Box 7)
- Business Records, 1957-1969, Series 4:; (Boxes 7-9; 2.4 linear ft.)
  Cash disbursements are mainly for Howard Wise's travel and entertainment expenses. Memoranda and correspondence between Cleveland and New York Galleries include debit and credit memoranda and concern sales, inventory, and shipments.
  The notebooks (64 small pocket volumes) contain brief notes on paintings, names and addresses, appointments and schedules, reminders, and a few lecture notes. Sales records consist of accounts paid, arranged by purchaser, and copies of sales receipts arranged chronologically.
  - Addresses, 1957, undated (Box 7)
  - Appointment Calendar, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Art Purchases (Box 7)
    - Europe, 1957-1959, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - United States, 1956-1958 (Box 7)
  - Artists Affiliated with Howard Wise Gallery (lists), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Balance Sheet, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Bank Reconciliation, 1960, undated (Box 7)
  - Budget, Promotion, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Cash Disbursements, 1957-1961, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Employees, 1959-1964 (Box 7)
  - Exhibition Schedules, 1964-1966 (Box 7)
  - "Gallery Notes" (newsletter of Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture), 1959-1961 (Box 7)
  - Inventories (include consignments), 1958-1961 (Box 7)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence between Cleveland and New York Galleries, 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - Notebooks, 1957-1964, (4 folders; 64 vols. in 14 packages) (Box 7)
  - Notes regarding Consignments, Loans, Sales, 1959-1961 (Box 7)
  - Paid Bills (Cleveland), 1956-1961, (12 folders) (Box 8)
  - Paid Bills (New York) (Box 8)
    - Abbey, 1963-1968 (Box 8)
    - Alpha, 1960-1965 (Box 8)
    - Art-Cart, 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - Circle Foto, 1964-1968 (Box 8)
    - Clark, Fred, 1960-1965 (Box 8)
    - Con Edison, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
    - Frank's Hardware, 1965-1969 (Box 8)
    - Ginnever, Chuck, 1960-1963 (Box 8)
    - Holmes Electric Protective Co, 1960-1968 (Box 8)
    - New York Telephone, 1965-1968 (Box 8)
    - Pauley, Hal, 1964-1967 (Box 8)
    - Schlemowitz, Abram, 1961-1963 (Box 8)
    - Thorn's Transfer, 1962 (Box 8)
  - Press Releases, 1961-1965 (Box 8)
  - Rental Plan ("Art for the Home") (Box 8)
    - Completed Agreements, 1958-1960s (Box 8)
    - General Information and Sample Contracts, circa 1958 (Box 8)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Gallery Artists, 1960s (Box 8)
  - Sales Records (Box 8)
    - Accounts Paid (A-R, by client), 1957-1961, (6 folders) (Box 8)
    - Accounts Paid (S-Z, by client), 1957-1961, (5 folders) (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous Records, 1957-circa 1960, Series 5:; (Box 9; 3 folders)
  Miscellaneous records consist of writings by Howard Wise and Douglas MacAgy and photographs of the Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture, Cleveland.
  - Photographs - Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture, Cleveland (interior and exterior views), 1957-1958 (Box 9 (hol))
  - "The Status of Art in Cleveland" by Howard Wise (text of address delivered at Women's City Club of Cleveland, January 14, 1960), circa 1959-circa 1960 (Box 9 (hol))
  - "Vox Pop" by Douglas MacAgy (article), undated (Box 9 (hol))